[Music]
hi everyone this is RI welcome to
tricentis tasa automation tutorial as
you all know I've already published 73
YouTube videos covering beginners level
advanced
level beginers level intermediate level
and advanced level concepts of tricentis
tasa automation
so from few videos onwards I've started
teaching you the realtime scenarios
where you might encounter different
types of obstacles and how can we solve
those obstacles while automating the
test cases by using trient tasa please
do subscribe to the channel click on
Bell icon you'll receive notifications
whenever I publish more videos don't
forget to like and share the video thank
you this is is our lesson 74 in terms of
overall tricentis Tas automation
training and this is obstacle 32 in
terms of realtime scenarios in this
lesson I'm going to teach you how can we
solve an obstacle where you need to sort
all 10 numbers displaying on the screen
in sequential
order by using the methods like do while
Loops if El statements
so now let us go and see in detail what
is the obstacle that we need to solve
for so here is the obstacle list that we
started working on and if you scroll
down so this is our obstacle that we are
going to solve for bubble sort which is
categorized as hard let us go for it let
us understand what is the obstacle that
we need to solve for
so I can read here sort the number from
1 to
9 click on Swap if the left number is
greater than the right number inside the
blue
bubble otherwise click next so the blue
text field on the bottom left will
display keep sorting until all the
numbers are correctly sorted so here
these are the 10 numbers that are
displaying now we need to sort in
ascending order if the number on right
side is less than the number on left
side you need to click swap so now 1 is
less than 4 so that means the condition
is satisfied so if the condition
satisfies left number less than right
number then you need to click next again
if left number is less than right number
then again you need to click on
next if left number is greater than
right number you need to click on
Swap then click next again your left
number is less than right number so
simply you can go to next so here your
left number is greater than right number
click on
Swap so this way keep performing the
actions until all the numbers are
sorted so now you can see all the
numbers are sorted and your button also
changed perfect you did it so until you
sort all the numers successfully your
button remains as keep sorting okay so
now how can we automate this by using
trient tasa let us go to trient tasa so
as usual we are going to capture the
objects that are required for automation
under module section in obstacles folder
right click on this obstacles folder
select
scan
application so this is the application
that you would like to automate click on
scan
so if you are not able to capture the
objects in the right way you are going
to struggle in automating this
particular scenario what we need to do
observe clearly for here I need to
capture swap next and keep sorting
buttons first let's do one thing simply
select
Swap and this is uniquely identified
next this is uniquely identified keep
sorting this is also uniquely identified
now you need to capture this
bubble left number and the right number
so for that expand this one so you don't
you're not seeing that bubble right so
what you need to do you need to expand
the filter by clicking right side still
I don't see again click here now I can
see the bubble how where so if you
scroll up so this is your bubble so if
you
see your bubble left number is one that
and then your bubble right number is
eight and this is your bubble so let's
expand this now select the bubble If You
observe closely the bubble has the
property called inner text 18 this is
dynamic so you should not rely on this
inner text instead uncheck this one
rely on your class name and rename this
as bubble to identify the object
correctly and then this is your first
number check this one again your first
number has an inner text of one so these
numbers are not unique these are all
Dynamic so uncheck this inner text and
check the class name and here let's
rename this as first in the same way the
second
one this is my second number inner text
is right now eight but in future it
might not be eight so that's why remove
this and check class name and rename
this as
second but if You observe closely these
two are now not uniquely identified
because for this objects class name is
num tag is div for this object class
name is num tag is div now I need to
make these two numbers identify uniquely
how can I do that I can use identify
object by index select this now my first
number has an index of one select this
in the same way your second number has
an index of two select this one now you
can see here your num one and second
number are uniquely
identified so you should not forget that
what are the things that you should not
forget expand the filter to identify the
bubble and you need to change the bubble
property by removing inner text add
class name and then same applies for
number one number two remove inner text
add class name but for number one and
number number two we are making these
two identified as unique by introducing
the identify by index so now let us name
this module with the name of your
obstacle copy
this and
then paste it here and save
the
module and close your X
scan let's come back here now so if you
scroll down fully so this is the
obstacle that we captured so come here
now this is the module that we captured
I can see bubble first number second
number swap next keep sorting so now let
us automate the test case to automate
the test case let us concentrate on left
section which is test case section right
click on this obstacles folder obstacles
test case folder and create test
case and paste
the and name the test case with obstacle
name double click on this now let us
automate the test case to automate the
test case what is the method that you
would like to use so if You observe
closely first I'm going to perform
action either swap or next for the first
two numbers
and then again I'm going to perform
strap or next for the second two pair of
numbers so like that I'm going to keep
going until all the numbers have sorted
that means I can use I can use the loops
okay so let us go back here
now right click and select do statement
here create do statement select this one
so under do statement
you will have a loop and
condition now under Loop let me first
introduce weight let me introduce a
weight right click here ADD test step
I'm going to say weight T box weight I'm
going to wait
for 500 milliseconds okay
so why I'm introducing weight because to
before you you perform any action within
the loop I want to introduce a weight
now my first Loop is to check your inner
text or to capture the inner text into a
buffer what I'm going to do here I'm
going to Simply drag this module into a
loop first I come to my first bubble
right now I would like to buffer the
first number within the bubble I would
like to buffer the first number into a
variable so here what I'm going to do
expand
this and here I would like to buffer the
number how can I buffer the number by
using inner
text inner text equal to here
I'm going to buffer into num one
variable and your action mode should be
buffer now I have buffered your first
number into a variable so once that is
done I have to compare
if your second number is less than first
number if your second number is less
than first number you need to click on
Swap so how can we do that I would like
to introduce IFL statement so again come
to Loop right click and here select
create if
statement so under if statement what I
would like to do now I have to check if
your second number is less than your
first
number let's come here I'm going to
again drag this entire module onto the
condition so here now I'm going to make
sure that rename this step as check if
second number is less
than
first so to so to compare that what I'm
going to do come to your second number
because first number we have already
captured into a buffer so second number
inner
text
is less than so what I'm going to do if
the second number inner text is less
than
your first number which is stored under
buffer so hence what I'm going to do
here first your data type needs to be
changed okay change it to numeric that
is first and foremost thing that you
need to do and here
now second number in N Text is less
than your first number which is stored
under buffer so to call the buffer open
curly braces capital B open Square
braces your
buffer variable name n
M1 close Square braces close curly
braces so here what we are doing we are
verifying if the inner text of your
second number is less than the inner
text of first number which we stored
under buffer so we need to verify this
just specify it as
verify okay so if this condition is true
then what we need to do we need to swap
it so hence if this condition is true
then then again under then drag this
module onto then
condition and here you need to click on
Swap button so here I'm going to rename
this
as click
swap so
here against swap enter X so what are we
doing here under if condition I'm first
verifying the the condition if your
second number is less than first number
then I'm clicking on
Swap else you need to click on where you
need to click on next button so for that
again what I'm going to do here
simply drag this module onto your
Loop and
here after if condition if this
condition is not
satisfying then you need to click next
button I came out of if statement okay
so here
simply enter X against next button so
that is done and then I'm going to
repeat this until when I'm going to
repeat all this every time again it is
going to verify if the right is less
than left or not if right is not less
than left then you need to click on next
right so I have to do
this until when until my button is
displaying as keep
sorting once everything is sorted then
your button will be changing to
something else instead of keep sorting
so that's why what is my condition for
this do Loop statement just simply drag
this and drop here to the do condition
and here rename this as check if
sorting needed or not okay how can I
check that expand this
one I have to perform this
looping until I have the inner text of
this button as keep sorting so simply
come here verify the inner text inner
text equal
to
keep
sorting so here I'm going to select it
as
verify so let me explain the same thing
again here now okay
so what we are doing first I have
introduced a dual
Loop so do statement will have Loop
statement and condition what is the loop
I'm asking tasar to
perform sequence of operations under
Loop first I am buffering the first
number within the bubble so let me read
name
this
as
buffer the first
number once I buffer the first
number then I am verifying if the second
number is less than first number by
using IF else statement that's why
within the loop I have introduced IFL
statement how I'm ifying I am verifying
the inner text of Second
number is less than your first number
which is stored under buffer once that
is done if condition meets then I am
clicking on
Swap and then come out of if
statement if this condition does not
meet you need to click on next
button right so I'm repeating this Loop
until I meet the condition where the
button name is keep
sorting so now let
us change the status of your test case
as
completed save the test case let's go
back to application let me click on try
again so now right click and run in
scratchbook
now you can see here it is performing
swap if your second number is less than
your first number and it is clicking on
next if the condition does not meet so
it should sort all the numbers you can
see here now
Till There is one number which is not
sorting in correct sort
order so now this is done that means the
test case whatever we automated is
correctly working see now you can now
you can see 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 so let me
try again let me rerun this again okay
let's go back here right click and run
in scratchbook
now you started comparing the two
numbers based on the condition that we
entered if the right number is less than
left number then it is performing swap
otherwise it is per performing next so
now you can see all the numbers are
sorted
correctly so the do Loop is quitting as
soon as your button name changes to
perfect you did it that means keep
sorting inner text is changed to perfect
you did it so that is when the loop will
come
out so hope you all understand the
concept so this is really very very
important how can you sort all the
numbers by using two Loop and then if
then statements so if you have any
queries leave your queries in the
comment box I'll try to respond to your
queries thank
you hope you all understand how can we
solve an obstacle where you need to sort
the numbers that are displaying on
screen by using do and while loop
methods and and if else
statements please do subscribe to the
channel click on Bell icon you'll
receive notifications whenever I publish
more videos don't forget to like and
share the video thank you
[Music]